Nasr Syed . Jarvis Consulting

I am highly ambitious Software Engineer looking to break his way into the field of Data Analytics. My academic background consists of a Bachelor of Engineering (B.Eng) in Electrical Engineering from Ryerson University and a Data Engineering certification from IBM. My latest work experience consists of a Data Engineer role at CIBC under the Enterprise Data Hub department under Jarvis Consulting Group. Prior to my employment at Jarvis, I have been an Electrical Engineer for about three years, with the last six months in Project Management at top-name firms located in Toronto. As displayed by my successful track record, I am someone who thrives and pushes himself to be an engineer of the highest calibre. I decided to make the switch into the Software/Big Data world after my exposure to the field after my own personal research into this area. What intrigued me was the sheer value of data and the impact it has in every sector of the economy. Now having found my true passion, I am determined to impact the world of big data and software.

Skills

Proficient: Java, Python, Linux/Bash, Microsoft Azure Cloud, RDBMS/SQL, Agile/Scrum, Git/GitFlow/GitHub

Competent: Docker, DataBricks Notebooks, Hadoop/Hive, Cloud platforms (GCP,AWS,MS Azure), Numpy/Pandas

Familiar: Spark, Scala, MongoDB, HTTP Requests, Apache Cassandra

Jarvis Projects

Project source code: https://github.com/jarviscanada/jarvis data eng NasrSyed

Linux Cluster Monitoring Agent [GitHub]: Architected a routine monitoring agent script which tracked a cluster of nodes/servers running on CentOS 7 Linux distribution. Bash scripts retrieving host hardware, CPU and Memory usage were deployed, and provisioned via Docker. Results were periodically stored into a PostgreSQL database via crontab job.

Core Java Apps [GitHub]:

- Grep App: Implemented a Java 8 application in IntelliJ that takes in parameters for a regex pattern and returns matching lines containing this pattern from all text files in the target directory to an output text file. Used recursive methods for the main functionality of the application and incorporated various methods to handle specific tasks, and merged together in a for-loop.
- JDBC App: Architected a Java 8 application that connects to a RDBMS (PSQL) database containerized in Docker to perform basic CRUD operations between an object and respective database, through core functions of JDBC. Functionality of this program utilized core concepts such as DAO and DTO, incorporated into the methods, and SQL queries were processed successfully.

Highlighted Projects

ETL Project for Market Exchange Data: Extracted exchange rate data from all countries from CSV, JSON and XML files into a dataframe, transformed currency data, and loaded data into a target CSV file. Formulated logging function to track/provide timestamps and logging details of ETL process. (Python, Pandas)

SQL Database on IBM Db2: Utilized raw CSV data provided by Chicago Data Portal on socioeconomic factors and crime data. Stored datasets on IBM Db2 and derived SQL queries for insights on health, safety, and environments of Chicago schools. (MySQL, IBM Db2)

Professional Experiences

Data Engineer, CIBC (Feb 2022 - June 2022): Migrated data from CIBC's on-premises data storage to Microsoft Azure Cloud storage accounts from parquet to delta format as a part of the Data Lake team in the Enterprise Data Hub department. Responsible for writing DDL/DML scripts, validating metadata in SQL (Azure Data Studio/Oracle DB), and configuring/running ADF pipelines in Microsoft Azure. Developed scripts in DataBricks with Python and Scala to parse, clean and validate data partitions and ensure consistency in ADF pipeline runs. Established in-house documentation for Microsoft Azure deployment standards/usage and debugging/troubleshooting ADF pipelines and migration processes.

Data Engineer, Jarvis (Oct 2021-Present): Worked in an Agile/Scrum environment to work on software projects with a team of Software Engineers. Worked as part of a team to design, implement, test and deploy features on a product. Daily scrum meetings were held to discuss issues and to set goals for the day. Weekly code reviews were done by senior

developers to ensure code works as expected and to meet standards. Worked on features via tickets and uploaded code to GitHub for version control. To manage branches and features, the GitFlow methodology was followed on all projects.

Project Coordinator/Electrical Engineer, Morrison Hershfield (Apr 2021 - Oct 2021): Spearheaded technical management and oversight of 100+ electrical projects for 5G tower upgrades. Assisted senior engineers with electrical design and led weekly update meetings on project status.

Electrical Engineer, The HIDI Group (Jan 2019 - Jan 2021): Engineered electrical system design for buildings in accordance with OBC, OESC & other relevant codes/standards. Designed electrical drawings in AutoCAD.

Design Technician, Telecon (May 2018 - Dec 2018): Liased with Project Engineers, Project Coordinators and CAD technicians to complete Hydro pole assessments. Designed CAD drawings from concept to final release.

Education

Ryerson University (2013-2017), Bachelor of Engineering - Electrical Engineering, Electrical and Computer Engineering

Miscellaneous

- Data Engineering Professional Certificate IBM
- Learning World History
- Reading Current Book: 12 Rules for Life by Jordan Peterson
- Health/Fitness
- Snowboarding
- A wide variety of media/entertainment